<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Alla codifica dell'esercizio 1, si aggiungono i nuovi tag visti a lezione-->

<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "tei_all.dtd">

<TEI>
    <teiHeader xml:lang="it">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Wonderful Wizard of Oz: edizione digitale</title>
                <author>Baum, Lyman Frank (1856, 1919)</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>codifica di</resp>
                    <name>Fabio Melasi</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    Edizione digitale realizzata in <date when="2023-04">aprile 2023</date>.
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Fabio Melasi</distributor>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>
                        Questa edizione digitale è libera e diffusa attraverso <ref target="https://github.com/Pinghie/codifica_fm">GitHub</ref>.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    La codifica riguarda i primi 3000 caratteri del libro.
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="book">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Lyman Frank</forename>
                                <surname>Baum</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <title>The Wonderful Wizard of Oz</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Project Gutenberg</publisher>
                            <date when="2014-1-6">6 gennaio 2014</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>La codifica del testo è stata realizzata rispettando le linee guida TEI P5 come esercitazione del corso di Codifica dei Testi dell'Università di Pisa.</p>
                <p>L'esercizio consiste nella codifica di un testo a piacere di 3000 caratteri.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">Inglese</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation>
                <date when="1900">1900</date>
                <rs type="city">Chicago, Illinois</rs>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head type="chapter">Chapter I - The Cyclone</head>
                
                
                <p n="1">
                    <lb n="1"/>
                    <name type="person">Dorothy</name> lived in the midst of the great <name type="place">Kansas</name> prairies, with Uncle
                    <lb n="2"/>
                    <name type="person">Henry</name>, who was a farmer, and Aunt <name type="person">Em</name>, who was the farmer’s wife. Their
                    <lb n="3"/>
                    house was small, for the lumber to build it had to be carried by wagon
                    <lb n="4"/>
                    many miles. There were four walls, a floor and a roof, which made one
                    <lb n="5"/>
                    room; and this room contained <list><item>a rusty looking cookstove,</item><item>a cupboard for 
                    <lb n="6"/>
                    the dishes,</item><item>a table,</item><item><num>three</num> or <num>four</num> chairs,</item><item>and the beds</item></list>. Uncle <name type="person">Henry</name>
                    <lb n="7"/>
                    and Aunt <name type="person">Em</name> had a big bed in one corner, and <name type="person">Dorothy</name> a little bed in
                    <lb n="8"/>
                    another corner. There was no garret at all, and no cellar—except a
                    <lb n="9"/>
                    small hole dug in the ground, called a cyclone cellar, where the family
                    <lb n="10"/>
                    could go in case one of those great whirlwinds arose, mighty enough to
                    <lb n="11"/>
                    crush any building in its path. It was reached by a trap door in the
                    <lb n="12"/>
                    middle of the floor, from which a ladder led down into the small, dark
                    <lb n="13"/>
                    hole.
                </p>

                
                <p n="2">
                    <lb n="14"/>
                    When <name type="person">Dorothy</name> stood in the doorway and looked around, she could see
                    <lb n="15"/>
                    nothing but the great gray prairie on every side. Not a tree nor a
                    <lb n="16"/>
                    house broke the broad sweep of flat country that reached to the edge of
                    <lb n="17"/>
                    the sky in all directions. The sun had baked the plowed land into a
                    <lb n="18"/>
                    gray mass, with little cracks running through it. Even the grass was
                    <lb n="19"/>
                    not green, for the sun had burned the tops of the long blades until
                    <lb n="20"/>
                    they were the same gray color to be seen everywhere. Once the house had
                    <lb n="21"/>
                    been painted, but the sun blistered the paint and the rains washed it
                    <lb n="22"/>
                    away, and now the house was as dull and gray as everything else.
                </p>
                
                <p n="3">
                    <lb n="23"/>
                    When Aunt <name type="person">Em</name> came there to live she was a young, pretty wife. The sun
                    <lb n="24"/>
                    and wind had changed her, too. They had taken the sparkle from her eyes
                    <lb n="25"/>
                    and left them a sober gray; they had taken the red from her cheeks and
                    <lb n="26"/>
                    lips, and they were gray also. She was thin and gaunt, and never smiled
                    <lb n="27"/>
                    now. When <name type="person">Dorothy</name>, who was an orphan, first came to her, Aunt <name type="person">Em</name> had
                    <lb n="28"/>
                    been so startled by the child’s laughter that she would scream and
                    <lb n="29"/>
                    press her hand upon her heart whenever <name type="person">Dorothy</name>’s merry voice reached
                    <lb n="30"/>
                    her ears; and she still looked at the little girl with wonder that she
                    <lb n="31"/>
                    could find anything to laugh at.
                </p>

                <p n="4">
                    <lb n="32"/>
                    Uncle <name type="person">Henry</name> never laughed. He worked hard from morning till night and
                    <lb n="33"/>
                    did not know what joy was. He was gray also, from his long beard to his
                    <lb n="34"/>
                    rough boots, and he looked stern and solemn, and rarely spoke.
                </p>

                <p n="5">
                    <lb n="35"/>
                    It was <name type="animal">Toto</name> that made <name type="person">Dorothy</name> laugh, and saved her from growing as gray
                    <lb n="36"/>
                    as her other surroundings. <name type="animal">Toto</name> was not gray; he was a little black
                    <lb n="37"/>
                    dog, with long silky hair and small black eyes that twinkled merrily on
                    <lb n="38"/>
                    either side of his funny, wee nose. Toto played all day long, and
                    <lb n="39"/>
                    <name type="person">Dorothy</name> played with him, and loved him dearly.
                </p>

                <p n="6">
                    <lb n="40"/>
                    Today, however, they were not playing. Uncle <name type="person">Henry</name> sat upon the
                    <lb n="41"/>
                    doorstep and looked anxiously at the sky, which was even grayer than
                    <lb n="42"/>
                    usual. <name type="person">Dorothy</name> stood in the door with Toto in her arms, and looked at
                    <lb n="43"/>
                    the sky too. Aunt <name type="person">Em</name> was washing the dishes.
                </p>

                <p n="7">
                    <lb n="44"/>
                    From the far north they heard a low wail of the wind, and Uncle <name type="person">Henry</name>
                    <lb n="45"/>
                    and <name type="person">Dorothy</name> could see where the long grass bowed in waves before the
                    <lb n="46"/>
                    coming storm. There now came a sharp whistling in the air from the
                    <lb n="47"/>
                    south, and as they turned their eyes that way they saw ripples in the
                    <lb n="48"/>
                    grass coming from that direction also.
                </p>

                <p n="8">
                    <lb n="49"/>
                    Suddenly Uncle <name type="person">Henry</name> stood up.
                </p>

                <p n="9">
                    <lb n="50"/>
                    <q>“There’s a cyclone coming, <name type="person">Em</name>,”</q> he called to his wife. <q>“I’ll go look
                    <lb n="51"/>
                    after the stock.”</q> Then he ran toward the sheds where the cows and
                    <lb n="52"/>
                    horses were kept.
                </p>
                    
                <p n="10">
                    <lb n="53"/>
                    Aunt <name type="person">Em</name> dropped her work and came to the door. One glance told her of
                    <lb n="54"/>
                    the danger close at hand.
                </p>
                
                <p n="11">
                    <lb n="55"/>
                    <q>“Quick, <name type="person">Dorothy</name>!”</q> she screamed. <q>“Run for the cellar!”</q>
                </p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>